Register of the Poland. Poselstwo (Yugoslavia) Records
Hoover Institution Archives
Poland. Poselstwo (Yugoslavia) records,
1921-1940
XX676
Poland. Poselstwo (Yugoslavia)
2 manuscript boxes (0.8 linear feet)
Hoover Institution on War, Revolution, and Peace Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence, dispatches, reports, telegrams, and diplomatic agreements, relating to Polish-Yugoslav relations and to Polish and Yugoslav diplomacy during World War II.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Historical Note
Polish legation in Yugoslavia.
Scope and Content Note
The records of the Polish Legation in Yugoslavia consist of decoded telegrams exchanged with the Foreign Ministry Headquarters in Warsaw, and of correspondence, reports, and diplomatic agreements.
The material relates to Polish-Yugoslav relations and to Polish and Yugoslav diplomacy in general, and gives a fragmentary insight into the functioning of a Polish diplomatic post during the interwar period.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the repository's online public access catalog.
Subjects
Poland--Foreign relations--Yugoslavia.; Yugoslavia.; Yugoslavia--Foreign relations--Poland.; World War, 1939-1945--Diplomatic history.; World War, 1939-1945--Poland.; World War, 1939-1945--Yugoslavia.; World War, 1939-1945.; Poland.
Series Description
- Correspondence, 1939. (Box 1)
  Letters expressing sympathy and solidarity with Poland after the German invasion, 1939 September-December
- Decoded Telegrams, 1936-1940. (Box 1)
  Includes reports in the form of telegrams
- Economic File, 1939-1940. (Box 1)
  Reports and correspondence related to the opening of the Polish-Yugoslav Chamber of Commerce, arranged chronologically
- Political File, 1921-1940. (Box 1-2)
  Protest notes, reports, and treaties, arranged alphabetically by physical form
Container List
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1939. (Box-folder 1: 1)
- DECODED TELEGRAMS, 1936-1940
  - General
    - 1936
      - Incoming (Folder 1: 2)
      - Outgoing (Folder 1: 3)
    - 1938 - Incoming and outgoing (Folder 1: 4)
    - 1939 - Incoming and outgoing (Folder 1: 5)
    - 1940
      - Incoming, January 4-June 29 (Folder 1: 6)
      - Outgoing, January 11-June 25 (Folder 1: 7)
  - Political developments
    - 1936
      - Incoming (Folder 1: 8)
      - Outgoing (Folder 1: 9)
    - 1937
      - Incoming (Folder 1: 10)
      - Outgoing (Folder 1: 11)
- ECONOMIC FILE, 1939-1940.
  Reports and correspondence related to the opening of the Polish-Yugoslav Chamber of Commerce
  - 1939 (Folder 1: 12)
  - 1940 (Folder 1: 13)
- POLITICAL FILE, 1921-1940
  - Protest notes
    - Arrest of Jagiellonian University professors
      - General, 1939-1940 (Folder 1: 14)
      - Correspondence, 1940 (Folder 1: 15)
    - Repressions against the general population. Notes addressed to the Yugoslav Foreign Ministry, 1940 (Folder 1: 16)
  - Reports
    - Poland, Conditions in both zones of occupation of, 1940 (Folder 1: 17)
    - Yugoslavia, Conditions in
      - 1939
        - February-April (Folder 1: 18)
        - May-June (Folder 1: 19)
        - July-August (Folder 1: 20)
        - October-November (Folder 1: 21)
      - 1940
        - January-February (Folder 1: 22)
        - March-April (Folder 1: 23)
        - May-August (Folder 1: 24)
  - Treaties (Box 2)
    - General. List of international treaties signed by Yugoslavia, 1925-1938 (Folder 2: 1)
    - Air transportation. Text, 1938 (Folder 2: 2)
    - Commerce, 1921-1923
      - Correspondence
        - 1921 (Folder 2: 3)
        - 1922 (Folder 2: 4)
        - 1923 (Folder 2: 5)
        - 1928 (Folder 2: 6)
        - 1939 (Folder 2: 7)
      - Texts (Folder 2: 8)
    - Cultural exchange, 1938 (Folder 2: 9)